welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay we're gonna begin
welcome to the stoah I am the steward of
the stoah Peter Lindbergh and I'm
viewing the Stowe as a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge at this moment
and this is not only a place for us to
practice and talk about stoicism but
it's a place to explore with new
practices and in psycho technologies and
kind of put us at the edge of our
thinking and we have a great great guest
today Michel Tremblay a friend of mine
who is in the stoical movement and he's
going to give a talk today about a stoic
training program how that will look so
I'll hand it over to Michael and in a
moment and he's going to give maybe
about a 20 minute talk and then we're
going to open up to question and answers
and how that's gonna work just write
down your question in the chat box and
then I will call your name and then just
unmute yourself and ask Michael your
question if you prefer I read your
question for on your behalf just
indicate that in the chat box as well
and we'll ask maybe a few questions but
the questions might go all the way to
the hour ending at the hour mark or we
might split up into some kind of group
facilitated conversation in different
breakout rooms so we're just gonna play
that by ear
stop being said I'm going to hand it
over to Michael
you
no uh let's just see you're muted right
now on me I did a mass mute so maybe
that's all I can unmute myself okay
great um it's my first time using zoom
so I'm still figuring it out um great hi
everybody thanks so much for coming
I'm just really exciting to see so many
people yeah hi max hi to see so many
people uh discussing stoicism are
interested in this topic I really like
nerding out about it so it's a it's it's
cool there's other people interested a
bit by myself I'm a PhD candidate at
Queen's University in Ontario Canada and
I study Epictetus there so I study
stoicism I'm doing a PhD in philosophy
and specifically what I study is I study
moral education in ancient Greek
philosophy specifically in epictetus but
I'm really interested in this question
so you didn't think of a lot of ethics
as being concerned with what is good and
what is bad and was right and wrong and
I'm more so interested in this question
of moral education which is like given
that we have an established theory of
what is Right wrong how do we transform
ourselves to be the kind of people that
can act successfully on our
understanding right wrong and good and
bad so not so much this question of what
virtue is but this question of how do I
go about cultivating virtue and
transforming myself and I think that
that's just a much more interesting
question it was a question that we've
lost interest in in contemporary
philosophy but was really at the forint
drip philosophy this idea of self
transformation and a lot of the times
when we engage in ethics and engage in
philosophy it can be easy to lose sight
of that and what makes up
this special it was he was actually
teeth her right so he actually taught
stoic philosophy and what we have from
him as we have from him an outline of
how a program of moral education would
function and work so I'm gonna talk a
bit about that program the three kind of
areas of study the three top point and
three disciplines sometimes been called
and how trainee min and those would look
great yeah so I guess questions are at
the end so we'll just get started
so--but I'm gonna assume everybody has
kind of working background and the
stoicism will try to fill some things in
and then I'll go from there and I'm also
trying to do this in a way where it can
be applicable or interesting for those
who don't agree with stoicism value that
the only thing that matters is what is
up to us or the only good and bad is
virtue advice and try to look at some
ways of working this program in for
people with different value systems as
well great so the first part of
epictetus is program moral education
divides into three portions and each
portion needs to be mastered
sequentially so they can be all be
studied but you need to master the first
before you can master the second before
you can master the third and it's only
after the mastering of all three to be
achieved virtue and become you know
sages and and virtuous wise individuals
so these kind of go in a progressing
order so beginning with the first one
this is the one that is famously
corresponds to physics which is about
the way things are
but really what epictetus talks about
being it's about mastering desire and
aversion and what desire and aversion
are are those are the strongest impulses
that we feel they're the strongest
emotional or physiological responses we
feel towards things and what epictetus
points out is that desire and aversion
correspond to value judgments about good
and bad right so good as we think of
good as being the best kind of thing the
thing that always benefits us this is
like a technical term and then bad as
being the worst kind thing the thing
that always harms us so desire and
aversion are these feelings that we feel
that correspond to these two kinds of
value judgments and when you begin life
and you don't begin like studying
philosophy you develop these kind of
value judgments unintentionally and
uninformed and then what happens is you
end up suffering or being at the mercy
of these emotional physiological
responses because you view the wrong
kinds of things as being good and bad so
the way to master designer version is
epictetus fezzes not to not feel desired
average it's not to be apathetic but
it's the feel desire and aversion for
the correct kinds of things and so you
ask that the start of philosophy is we
want to be intentional about our value
system we want to be intentional about
what we view is good and bad and what we
feel desire an aversion for what we feel
pulled towards what we feel drawn away
from so we recognize this we want to
live intentionally and then what we do
is we mean next thing we do is we
actually suspend our judgments so we go
from people who function assuming things
are good and bad function feeling
designer versions and passions that
correspond to that anger and when we
think something wrongs us or happiness
when you think something benefits us and
we take a step back from that because
when we're in this mode this would
epictetus this is why it's the first
area of study is desires and aversions
when they're frustrated they correspond
to passions and passions
interrupts our capacity to reason
properly so if you're an untrained
person just beginning your philosophical
journey and you're starting to think
well you know what kind of philosophy do
I agree in agree with how do I want to
live your passions are going to pull you
around and they're going to disrupt your
capacity to reason so the first thing we
do is we suspend our judgments
then we take a step back and go okay I
don't know what good and bad is and then
the next thing we do is we look for a
standard a way to test that in a way to
evaluate that a way to make sense of the
world around us and so for epictetus
this is stoic philosophy but I think
this is good advice for anybody
whatever philosophy that would be you
take a step back to the very beginning
of philosophy is I want to live
intentionally and I want to live
correctly it's the very beginning then
the next thing you do is you take a step
back and you say well I hadn't been
living attention correctly so I don't
know and in a position of ignorance so I
take a step back from my commitments
from my value judgments and I look for a
way to make sense of the world I look
for a way to evaluate the world and what
you end up doing is is you either take
up stoicism you're taking about Kurian
ISM or a civilian ISM or some sort of
contemporary method of value
consequentialism utilitarianism the
ontology you find some way of making
sense of the world and evaluating good
of that good and bad things and good and
bad actions and then what you do is you
take that standard and you carefully
apply it to the world around you
cautiously intentionally and one at a
time so you do is you take a step back
from your value judgments you enter a
state of ignorance and then you
one-by-one reintegrate objects
situations people and yuria valuate them
with this standard with this philosophy
that you've developed this in epictetus
this program this is stoic Theory stoic
philosophy things that are good is is
virtue and things that are bad is vice
and you you apply that judgment to all
objects situations types of things you
pursued in the past types of things that
you've been afraid of in the past like
death or like well for popularity and
you go about reintegrating these objects
into your life carefully and one by one
and the point with this is this is that
this has to be the starting point of
philosophy because until we do this we
are just going to be disrupted by our
passions in a way that like if we try to
skip this step and you you skip
taking a position of ignorance and
slowly building and you just try to act
on what you would you endorse in terms
of theory your passions are gonna be a
disrupt at that capacity and you're not
gonna be able to act on what you think
is with you which you take in theory to
be the right thing so taking a step back
from this what I think the call for here
is is the first step of philosophy is to
recognize that your your value systems
and your beliefs influence your
motivations and influence your emotional
in your passionate States right so we
take that so then we say that it's
better to have no beliefs than to have
harmful beliefs and wrong beliefs so
what we do is we move from the state we
a recognition that our beliefs influence
our motivations and our emotional state
and then the next part of stoic training
is to do a schema skeptical and ignorant
position and then what we do is we
carefully one-by-one reintegrate beliefs
and reintegrate things into our value
system so this is the first step
mastering of desire and aversion is
Epictetus says and what I think is
really interesting about this is it's
just a call it's a call to live
intentionally and it's a call that a
flawed value system can be more harmful
than than nothing and I think that works
no matter your value system or no matter
if you don't agree with stone philosophy
all the way and then once we've done
that we should hopefully be motivated
with extremely strong passionate
producing emotions only towards the
kinds of things that we actually view is
good and the kinds of things that we
actually view is bad and this is just
and that would be the state of mastery
desire and aversion which takes time and
takes work but that's what we're looking
at so we're looking to get to so the
state were you know in a stoic terms I'm
not I'm aggrieved by a sense of by a
fear of death I'm not that's not
allowing me or preventing me from doing
the kinds of things I want to do I'm not
being tempted or coerced by other people
who are threatening me because my states
of passions and emotions are under
control so
I do this in 20 minutes when we move
ahead to the next one and they will talk
on flesh these out a bit further so
after you design a master designer and a
version that's the first step so you
assume you assume a sceptical position
you take on some sort of theory or some
sort of philosophy you apply it
carefully concerning things that are
good and bad not so very strong things
that are really really good and really
really bad then what we're left with
there after what we are motivated
towards is what corresponds with what's
good or what we take to be good and vice
versa
we still need a way to navigate things
that are less good so we needed a way to
navigate in the stoical sense this would
be how do we navigate a difference how
do we navigate our obligations the
things that are not virtue in Vice in
other senses this would just be you know
I've taken what my core value system is
perhaps that's pleasure
perhaps that's obligations to other
people perhaps that's some sort of
deontological content picture or
something like this and then I well what
do I do about these kind of in-between
states that don't seem to correspond
immediately or how do i how do I fill
these out and stoicism this would be
like how do I flesh out if I know I want
to be virtuous and I don't want to be
vicious how do I flesh out now my
obligations to other people my
obligations to my community to my body
what how I should act and all these
other in-between cases okay so the first
thing we do is we master our strong
desires and fears and then the next
thing we do is we move to fleshing out
how we should act in specific in
particular situations how we should act
in specific contexts giving us value
system right and so for a big penis this
is mastering what he calls impulse to
act an impulse not attack which is a
gentler form of impulse and this is the
this is the area which is is corresponds
to ethics who corresponds to particular
actions the first one corresponds to
physics because it's about understanding
the way the world is what do I take to
be good can take to be bad and
this is ethics as in given that this is
good and this is bad and this is the
value system I've adopted how now do I
act how now do i fulfill my obligations
to other people and other situations
and for epictetus I mean this is the
stoic picture they're very much
connected to this picture of of nature
right so so appealing to nature and
following our nature and that penis has
this picture of stoic rules so this
means is when I when I want to figure
out how I should act in situations what
I do is I appeal to different roles that
I have and different kinds of rules that
form a hierarchy so at the very top of
the hierarchy what I have is I have my
universal rule as a human being so when
I'm considering how I should act I never
act in a way that conflicts with this
universal rule as a human being and that
universal rule has some implications so
one of the implications is I don't do
things that conflict with virtue I don't
do things that will be vicious but other
obligations we have as a human being is
to preserve our body right so I would
not you know if virtue and vice are all
that matters to me I'm not harmed if I
lose a hand in a substantial way but
it's still quite strange I still would
not want to be the kind of person who
selects to like self mutilate or selects
to harm my body so when I'm looking for
how to how to navigate particular
situations in particular ethical
situations what we do is we appeal to
our roles first of all as that as a
universal role as a human being our
universal role as as an animal and as a
rational animal and that means we we act
rationally and we respect our body and
our physical health when we can and then
the next way there's kind of this
hierarchy and we keep going through it
the next thing we do is we appeal to our
particular capacities so we appeal to we
appeal to our particular talents so we
could conflict against our nature if you
know you're trying to be kind of kind of
person you're not so you're trying in
your ethical pursuit to become an
extroverted person when you're really
fundamentally an introverted person or
you're trying to like things that
just don't fit with with your with your
nature and your capacity and your
dispositions
so what Epictetus would say here is in
these kind of situations just just
honestly appeal and reflect to your
capacities in your your physical
disposition and use that as information
and navigate specific situations
the next thing we do that we can appeal
to is we can appeal to our specific
relationships with other people
so we appeal to our universal rule is a
human being we appeal to our particular
rule which is our capacity our certain
capacities maybe we're born with a
certain disposition maybe we like logic
we like bath maybe we like music
maybe we're social and we follow along
those two tell us how to act and how to
structure and how to get our life and
the next thing you do is you look to
your rules in terms of your relationship
with other human beings so you look to
you say well am i and my mother and my
father am i a friend so on and so forth
and you flesh out that and you develop
that and so then now we start to get a
picture of how this is kind of a program
that has to progress sequentially so
one thing like one example that BTS uses
and he loves these examples and one that
I think's really interesting is he uses
the example of a of a father who is not
able to care for his daughters sick
right and he runs away from his daughter
he leaves the house he can't handle the
fact that his daughter might die and the
picture here or the ID here in this
situation is that this is someone who
has not mastered desire and aversion
this is someone who has not mastered the
first area of study they think that
death is a bad thing they're afraid of
their daughter dying they haven't come
to terms with what their alternate value
system should be under a stoic picture
and because of that that's interfering
with their capacity to fulfill their
obligation to other people he's not able
to fulfill his obligation as a father
because he's still afraid so we work
sequentially like this we master desire
and aversion and then we move to our
obligations to specific people and our
relationships and specific people our
relationships with ourselves and our
specific capacities and then the last
way to reflect how to structure our
lives is just choice and this is the
thing I like about epic tedious and I
like about stoicism is at the end of the
day if it doesn't conflict with reason
if it doesn't go against um you're each
reserving being it doesn't go against
your relation up betraying your
relationship with other human beings
there's gonna be some choices you make
in life which are just a matter of
choice just a matter of how you how you
choose choose to live so whether or not
you go into one career or another
whether or not you pursue one path or
another there's ultimately a part of it
is just up to you and I like that
there's there's this ethical system that
leaves space for that being a creative
endeavor and not something that you know
there's not necessarily going to be a
wrong answer in that regard and then the
last system so going through this in
order then once we're in a pretty good
position with that we move on to logic
and this is the last system which is
just how to reason properly and the idea
here is once we've mastered desire and
aversion so reviewing now really quickly
is trying to fit a lot here in to 20
minutes reviewing now we
say look I want to live intentionally
with intentional value system I
recognize that I'm ignorant and my
ignorance is harming you so I backup I
adopt a sceptical position I find a
philosophy that fits for me
this is epictetus is beginning to
philosophy then from there once I find a
value system that fits for me I
reconsider specific objects in relation
to that value system you know what now
does death mean to me what now does
popularity mean to me what now does my
career mean to me in relation to this
standard of judgment I've been giving in
the case of so it means they're not good
or bad because only virtual advice are
good and bad once we have that picture
in place then we move to this question
of how am I supposed to act in
particular situations how am I supposed
to act given this picture of good and
bad given how am I supposed to navigate
particular situations and as epictetus
asked us to appeal essentially to the
way the world is and appeal to
information about who we are naturally
as rational animals who we are
specifically as people with certain
talents and capacities and who we are
enter personally as members of the
communities and people with
relationships to other people and then
from there anything that doesn't fall
into those three steps can just be
creative can just be it can just uh you
can just pick you can just decide the
kind of life you want to live and then
the last system is logic so the idea
with logic is once I'm in that position
I want to cement that understanding
cement that way of thinking such that I
don't fall out of it Epictetus is talks
about cementing to the point where even
if you're drunk or even if you're
depressed or you fall into a manic state
you're not going to deviate from this
kind of knowledge and this was for him
was just the way of doing this was just
actually just studying logic studying
formal ways of fear of thinking studying
kind of logical fallacies the people
falling to and the main takeaway from
logic I would say there's two main
takeaways one is accenting cautiously
and intentionally so cultivating and
developing a mindfulness of your
situation your surroundings and the way
you're thinking
so that you're not forming beliefs or
judgments unintentionally and the second
way of doing it is to the second big
part of logic is assuming facilitating
consistency so what I mean by
consistency and he has these two parts I
wrote down here in our study of logic we
need to work to accept the consequence
consequences of what has been properly
derived so this is one thing that I work
at if someone presents and reasons a
good argument working on being the kind
of person that is responsive to reason
so even if it doesn't fit your biases
even if it doesn't fit what you wanted
the conclusion to be responding well
okay those premises lead to this
conclusion so I'm going to follow and
and accept that conclusion and then the
second part is that is accepting that if
one's premises produce an absurd or
necessary false conclusion you must
re-examine the premises so the second
idea of this is that if your beliefs
lead to an inconsistency or if your
beliefs lead to a problem doing the work
to reevaluate those beliefs and doing
the work to take a step back and think
about how you arrive to that conclusion
and I just think about this as like not
being able to function in a state of
cognitive dissonance not being able to
function in a state where you have
contradictory things simultaneously that
you believe becoming responsive to
reason in the fact that if you have a
set of beliefs to contradict with
another with one another that should be
motivating to the point where you reject
one and and you seek once again to
achieve consistency and realign those
beliefs so I
I try to there's just a lot of
information there which I tried to cover
as quickly as possible and I'll try to
summarize it one more time but what I
wanted to provide a picture of the main
takeaway there was I think sometimes
when we engage in stoicism it can be
like taken as some just some helpful
ideas or some concepts to work around
and you think about the dichotomy of
control or you think about these other
concepts but there really was a system
of following there really was a
progression at least in Epictetus school
that was meant to be followed in order
and there was a system that was meant to
be a lot of work and followed a specific
system and I tried to flesh a bit out of
what that was so the first was was
working to master your strong emotions
your passions by first assuming a
skeptical state and then carefully
re-evaluating things to be good or bad
next once we've done that learning to be
responsive to information about who we
are generally as rational creatures
particularly given our capacities and
given our specific relationships with
other people and learning to be
responsive to those reasons when
navigating specific situations and then
once we once you've done that the third
system of logic is learning - learning
to be responsive to reason in terms of
when you're having conversations when
you're thinking if there's some sort of
inconsistency evaluating where that
inconsistency is coming from and
rejecting one of the premises or at the
very least going back and reevaluating
them and if they're if the premises lead
to a conclusion soundly accepting that
conclusion even if it is not the one you
might want and the idea is definitely if
we progressively work on all three of
these we master these sequentially that
was the picture of how stoic training
was supposed to take place and I think
we get there a really interesting
picture of like a fleshed-out school and
something that's worth like a lifetime
of focusing on and developing so that
was a lot of information I tried try to
throw it out there and maybe we can
flush stuff out more in the chat and the
discussion
so thank you mm-hmm yeah yeah that's
good
yeah let's I like the idea of teasing
out those different those different
sections so I'm gonna ask Michael some
questions right now to warm us up if you
have any questions write it in the chat
box and then I'll call on you and you
can kind of unmute yourself or if you'd
like me to read it just indicate that
one thing I'm curious it's somewhat a
kind of a more personal question with
your relationship with stoicism but
related to something you just said how
did you find your way to stoicism how
did they grip you personally and then
you mentioned something about you know
you have to take this skeptical stance
and then you find out what philosophy
fits for you is there anything more you
can after that like how do you know the
philosophy fits for you besides having
that maybe that resonance with it yeah
great so I I'm firmly of the belief that
intentional living is better than on
intentional living like an examined life
is better than an unexamined life so
what I would hate to do I also want the
position that I'm pretty ignorant so I
would hate to like meet someone who's
like oh this is a really interesting
philosophy that works for me and be like
you're wrong you should be a stoic
you're ridiculous
I'm just not at that positioning yet so
for me what happened I think what what
draws a lot of people to someone what
drew me to stoicism was I like the idea
of accountability for the quality of
your life so one of the core values of
stoicism that I really like is this idea
that the quality of your life is up to
you it's not up to circumstances beyond
your control it's up to cultivating your
own character I like what follows from
that which is that every person has the
capacity for a good life every person
has the capacity you know if you take a
picture that there's certain conditions
required for a good life there some
people just are just just have bad lives
and will have bad locks um there's just
nothing that can be done about it and at
least intuitively if we can develop any
sort of system that saves us from that
claim I find it really appealing and
attractive and then another thing I like
about is I think a lot of people
underestimate the role of
you underestimate the role that kind of
your disposition or the way that you
think about things and I what I like
about stoicism like I'm being drawn as a
more towards Aristotelian ISM and other
schools as I studied more or I liked
what's awesome is it like
unapologetically emphasizes virtue it
says you know you can be happy on the
torture rack and it says like that is it
for a good life and there's something
quite inspiring about that and I hope
it's true it would be would be really
nice if it is and in terms of
discovering the philosophy that's right
for you I think that as I said and this
is part of what attracts me to moral
education you know if you're if you're
like if you're living with a slightly
different moral system but you're trying
your best every day to be good and
you're following intuitions and you're
living actively you're already in like
the top you know twenty ten percentile
of people like it really matters very
little to me if if what you take feel
ultimate ends is slightly different
obviously there's some things that are
going to be wrong in any system of like
murder or something like this or like
unjust murder out of anger or something
but most ethical systems are quite quite
similar in what they end up asking you
to do and kind of differ in terms of
their justification for why that's the
right thing to do um so I think I think
it's just like begin the journey and
open yourself up like Marcus Aurelius
talks about this and it's like I'm not
interested if I'm interested in the
truth you know if stoicism was wrong I
would I would I would want to know and
then learn that so be open in this
journey also for other possibilities
like I'm very cautious I like stoicism
it helps me be a better person but I'm
cautious of you know I consider myself
practicing stoic of attaching too
strongly to it as a label and you
mentioned your practice of stoic and I
know you do jujitsu and you became known
for that like the stoic guy who does it
Jitsu could you maybe speak
how jujitsu fits in your practice of
stoicism and how you practice stoicism
in other ways
yeah so in terms of practicing stoicism
I think that I think one of the best
ways so Epictetus talks about he says
suspend your judgment and then what
happens is you encounter new situations
and then you apply stoic theory to that
situation so you you suspend your
judgment you encounter new situation and
your supposed to evaluate it and if
things will correctly you go you know
these people are laughing at me it
doesn't matter to me you know it doesn't
have anything to do with vice and virtue
oh I've been like you know I've broken
my arm okay well not to set back to my
body but it's not a setback to my
character and I think one of the best
ways to engage in this kind of process
is to have difficult situations I mean
this is a concept that has talked about
about reimagining obstacles as tests and
I like to jitsu because it's like the
hardest thing that I found to do it's
really physically difficult you do it in
front of other people so when you lose
it's very embarrassing I mean I had an
MMA fight where I got seven stitches
here I got kneed in the head and got
physically harmed and you know 30 people
had paid money to come watch me fight so
it was like embarrassing in front of
them and I'd lost and these are just
like really really great opportunities
to just practice
because because because I'm not perfect
I have this intuition to fall back into
judging these things as bad things or
judging myself as being harm in these
situations and I think the more
difficult the situation the the better
the practice the the better practice it
is dealing with it and evaluating it and
that big penis makes this analogy to
wrestling it's all my favorite analogies
and he talks about you know you should
think about difficulties in your life
the way wrestlers think about training
partners and if you you know if a
wrestler came into a room and they could
beat everybody they'd be like coach get
me somebody better you know get me get
me different people to train with and if
you walk into a in your life you have no
difficulty every tease encourages kind
of cultivating this attitude of well
give me something tougher to do and that
being said because I'm not a sage you
know you don't want to go and do
something that's like brakes use way
outside your comfort zone I also find
you too nice because it's it's low
consequence martial arts is low
consequence it's high stress very
difficult but very low consequence um I
think perhaps something like public
speaking would be like that as well you
know something like this which is which
can be difficult but doesn't set you
back on in a substantial way is a great
way to to begin and practice that
training that's the main way that I that
I practice my stoicism another thing is
just it's just reflecting strongly ansan
so I believe another way that I practice
those thing that's really helpful is in
terms of working through emotions so one
thing we didn't get the chance to talk
about is the stoke theory of emotion
which is like really robust and really
really helpful and it's this idea that
our emotions correspond to beliefs about
the world and one thing stoicism really
helped me do was stop doing emotions as
being antagonistic or things that I
fought against and viewing emotions as
well this emotion is rooted in something
it's rooted in an evaluation about the
way the world is what evaluation is that
do I want to hold on to that evaluation
is that something I really believe in
and that's
I would say the place where besides
doing intentionally difficult things the
place where I practice stoicism the most
is in reflecting on my own emotional
life and being like why am I upset right
now
what judgment is producing that or even
why am i happy is that is that a
judgment that I want to have that kind
of process of self reflecting working
through that is both helpful to be a
stoic but also helpful in me like
learning about myself and and being
happier right right yeah I like that
because there's this impression that
stoic sure you know emotionless people
but I found that as well that to the
practice of stoicism it created what you
know the like how acceptance commitment
therapy called a cognitive diffusion I
can kind of like have some distance away
from my emotions and my thoughts so
they're not like conflated and I think
by having this I have a better
relationship with my emotional states
now I can kind of leaning into the more
well so I totally agree with that sauce
one more question then we'll open up to
the room the present moment was covert
and pandemic how do you how do you think
this relates to stoicism and how do you
think we can practice our stoicism er
used maybe this this whole crisis as an
opportunity mm-hmm
well I think it's like I think quite
stereotypically I mean it's quite
obviously like
a major issue that's like out of our
control in a lot of ways in some ways
it's actionable in terms of
self-isolation in terms of you know
perhaps looking out for your community
helping people with things they can't be
helped with and then just just isolate
yourself as much as possible but there's
a lot of fear and a lot of the anxiety
on something that was not produced
because anybody here's fault and it's
not a result of anybody hears mistakes
but nonetheless seems like it has the
capacity to harm and what we take to be
the most harmful way which is you know
death or extreme physical pain or
financial ruin right so you have this
you have this natural force that's out
of our control that will be harmful in
all the ways people take to be most
harmful if you don't just take the stoic
picture that vices is the only Beth yeah
that's a that's a huge huge test I think
one way stoicism can be helpful is just
in it just in a moment-to-moment therapy
and just in focusing reverting to the
dichotomy of control focusing on what
you can control and what is up to you
another way that it can be helpful is I
think in evaluating ourselves as
fundamentally rational animals we're
very lucky and I don't want to speak for
everybody's condition because I don't
know everybody situations but we're
lucky to be in this situation at a time
where we have the Internet at a time
where we have access to information
access to things like this where we can
hopefully still find ways to pass the
time that is meaningful and enjoyable
that is that is intellectual in a sense
and and connect with that aspect of our
lives
I think perhaps that's not that
difficult for the people in this session
right now these are probably people who
are you are probably more inclined
towards that but I think it's a good
opportunity for people to find oh
there's there's there's ways for me to
be happy in circumstances that I that I
thought I couldn't be happy and there's
another thing that Seneca talks about
that most people probably be familiar
with
which is that he recommends to you no
intentional discomfort so live in
poverty for a couple months and then for
the rest of your life you think oh is
this the worst that can happen to me is
this the worst that can happen and I
think situations like this provide
opportunities to realize the capacity
for people to step up the capacity for
people to inspire and work together and
still produce meaningful helpful
experiences even in the face of pandemic
so then hopefully when that passes that
gives us all a bit more confidence about
our robustness and about our anti
fragility than we might have assumed
their thoughts and I find that inspiring
helpful right right okay so let's turn
to the questions dawn you had a question
could you go off mute and ask it to
Michael yep absolutely thank you Peter
I'm behind Michael thank you so much for
that great overview you had a task and a
half there in 20 minutes and you just
about did it it's a great overview so
I'm fairly new to stoicism I'm a fresh
stoic as I like to call myself and I'm
definitely still finding my way and I
love the looking at the world and and
how we process things as good or bad and
taking that step back and having that
distance and but I wonder if there's a
risk and and I wonder if I've done it
myself
actually I've distanced myself too far
so that I don't judge too fast and I
don't you know I take the pause to think
about what my next step is can we do the
cognitive diffusion too much like can we
be at risk of putting too much distance
between ourselves and and what's
happening so that we become unfeeling so
that we become numb rather than
processing it in the right way if that
makes sense yeah absolutely um so one
thing that I think is helpful is like
looking at these schools in dialogue
with one another so stoicism was around
at the same time as a skepticism and
what skepticism would say is is
skepticism is Towson's both agreed look
suspend all your judgments until you can
know what's true and the skeptics would
say well you can't know what's true so
you just stay in that suspended state
and the Stoics say well no you can and
then you progress forward they just do
it cautiously and carefully so one thing
we can do especially if we're coming to
stoicism as a therapy which I think a
lot of people do is they say look I've
been sitting in these judgments I
recognize that these judgments are
causing me pain and suffering so I'm
going to take a step back from those
judgments that makes me feel better
and there becomes a fear of
reintegrating or there becomes a habit
of stepping away that just becomes so
practiced that we're not good at taking
the step back in and re incorporating
things into our value system I think
it's totally possible to do the Stoics
would advocate to you for you to avoid
it I think one thing that's helpful to
avoid it is to recognize that this is a
process so I think what a lot of people
want to do that or at least what I want
it to do I can speak for myself
is you say well if the goal of Stoicism
is to not be upset about what I
shouldn't be upset about I don't care
about anything done I have achieved the
goal of Stoicism and that's not the goal
of stoicism the goal of stoicism is to
feel the right way about things so not
be upset about things that don't deserve
your upsetness and to feel good about
things that you should feel good about
and when we think about it like that
there's there's that initial jump to
pull away too much but if we if we
forgive ourselves and we say look we're
Stoics in progress the the Stoics age
came once every 500 years I'm gonna
reintegrate things and in the process of
allowing myself to care about virtue and
care in the right way about my family
and my friends I'm gonna care about when
my friend made fun of me or I'm gonna
make a mistake and that's gonna hurt
when it shouldn't hurt and we have to
forgive ourselves and allow that
allowing mistakes in reintegration I
think if you do that it's a it's a
reasonable process that's really helpful
actually I love that I've just written
that down the key is not to feel things
but to feel the right way about things
that absolutely nails it I think
actually so say thank you and I won't
beat myself up quite so much when I'm
like am I feeling the right thing or are
we not feeling you anything at all so a
super helpful thank you so much I
appreciate that Thanks
cool Greg Lopez you had I think two
questions yes I do but I'll just take
one from now and if there's time I'll go
for the other one
thank you Michael I've been seeing your
work for a while and really appreciate
your master's thesis as well so I mean
question is about something interesting
you said at the very beginning where you
kind of as the first step of the stoic
is you kind of go
off on your own and suspend judgment
about your values and that's kind of the
first step and that's your take on that
or epictetus ISM your interpretation of
the discipline of action so Epictetus
was primarily teaching students away at
college I think according to my
understanding they were essentially
going away young men wealthy men who
were in training and they had the
opportunity to do this it's kind of like
a monk could the monk code of sorts
going off to college and so modern
Stoics when they pick this up don't have
that luxury we can't go off the stoic
college and go to a dorm and try to be
stoic and learn the theory first and
then walk around and suspend our
judgments about values so how would you
suggest modern Stoics go about living
their lives as family members and having
the jobs they have and stuff while still
holding their desires lately yeah great
this is great so thanks so much for the
question
yeah there was so much to cover I wish I
could pull into it so specifically what
he says is not to suspend desire and
version do-nothing says he's suspend is
not an aversion and limit yourself only
to impulse to act an impulse not to act
and these are technical terms but the
impulse is a gentler feeling and I mean
I'm Gregory I'm sure you're familiar
with this but it's it's something so the
example I would like to think of impulse
I think of it like oh I really want to
go get ice cream but if I don't get ice
cream I'm not gonna let that ruin my day
so there was an impulse I planned my day
I walked to the store I motivated myself
I recognized that that good would be
coming but it's a very gentle kind of
good and when I don't get the ice cream
I'm like okay that is not preferable but
I'm not crying I'm not angry I'm not
like mad oh why didn't I I'm not mad at
myself why don't I look up if the ice
cream place was open or not so the
epictetus is position is that these
these passions from my interpretation of
evocation that these passions are
produced by desire and aversion so he
says this outright passions are produced
alone by desire and aversion impulse to
act and not act which are when we we
judge something to be prefer
or dis preferred so preferable or not
preferable those don't produce passions
so those are able to motivate but they
don't leave us in a passionate State so
the ideas at the start it's not become
apathetic well is literally its
apathetic become not passionate but it's
not don't be motivated the picture is at
the starts motivate yourself gently okay
so I'm still going to do this job
interview I'm still going to go to work
I'm still going to on you know attempt
to impress that person I want to like me
but I'm gonna see I'm gonna view it as
this would be preferable if this happens
I don't let that strong feeling of I
really want this to come and then what
he's gonna say is eventually you're
gonna unlock that strong feeling but
you're just gonna point to virtue or
vice excellent thank you thank you Greg
you want to sneak your other question in
there um if you'd like it I'm not
cutting anybody else off um so the
second question is a little more
technical
it's about logic I know so you're
following peer had those model of logic
being uh associated with the third topic
but my understanding of the beginning of
stoic training is that you actually sit
down in a classroom learn some basic
logic and in order to suss out what the
stoic ideas of good and bad actually are
because you can derive that virtue is
the only good it's not an axiom and you
do that by looking at these
psychological components called
preconceptions prolepsis and you just
try to tease apart how your sussing good
and bad and getting a clearer idea of it
then you go and start your training so
I'm curious if you can say when did
logic come into play in epictetus
training program was it really just
toward the end or was there a touch at
the beginning and then it was focused on
at the end yeah great um I think that's
I think that's a fair assessment so when
I was talking about progressing this is
a progression of mastery so the idea is
you can't you you you study them
sequentially so you don't study them
sequentially you master them
sequentially the first one is the most
important because if you're in a
passionate state you're you're not going
to be receptive you know you take
someone who's in a passionate state you
sit them down and you derive why virtue
is the
good you're gonna be like like shut up
they're not gonna care i they're not
gonna be receptive to reason so we I
think the first thing is that to get
people out of that passion of state as
soon as possible but then obviously you
need some capacity to reason you need
some capacity to follow arguments to
study it is just that this cannot be
mastered until the end because a can't
be mastered until you've gone away with
passions and be well you're mastering is
you're mastering your knowledge your
solidifying your knowledge and the
transition towards virtue right and you
can't solidify what isn't there so you
have to be you have to be fleshed out
and in a good position in the first two
areas of study before you can solidify
um but we take it step back the third
area of study Epictetus says if the
first one corresponds to desire and
aversion and the second one corresponds
to impulses the third one corresponds to
a sense so the third area study
epictetus says is about a scent so it's
just about making sure that we give our
scent our belief we believed we judged
to be true the correct things in the
correct way and obviously you're going
to be doing that at any step you're just
not gonna be able to master it until
you've got your emotions and the
passions under control and yeah that's
the picture cool thank you
cool and we'll end off with a question
from Ben and he had two questions maybe
you can choose one and ask it to Michael
it's been a
let me see if a deist on the chat yeah
okay he's not a mute Ben can you hear us
okay I might have difficulty I'll ask
this question this mics not working kid
let me ask this first one okay so this
is from Ben how would you how would one
assess and evaluate progress in moral
education how do we determine whether or
not our training a stoicism or any other
intentional way of living is effective
yeah great um so in facism you're
progressing towards knowledge knowledge
of the way the world is and there's so
much aspects of still excite all day I
love and I would love to dig into but
their intellectual ists which means that
our motivation is derived from our
judgments and our emotions are derived
from our judgments so I pursue things
because I view them a certain way and I
feel anger sadness joy because I think
certain things have happened to me but I
evaluate to be good or bad so progress
would be thinking the right things about
things right we're gaining knowledge
successfully categorizing more and more
things in the correct way I'm
successfully thinking about more and
more things in the correct way this
would be progress and now in terms of
how you evaluate it I would say in
stoicism you can it's it's a very
personal philosophy you can evaluate it
by your physical state so instead ISM
lucky for us according to the Stoics God
has put us in a position where we can
achieve all things that are good and
avoid all things that are bad right
because what's good and bad is virtue in
Vikes so if you feel yourself being
frustrated or being feeling really
strong emotions about the about the
world this is because you're in the
Stoics perception you're putting value
judgments that are incorrect onto the
world so I think the way you would
evaluate progress and stoicism is your
equity
your feeling of tranquility your feeling
your capacity to deal with hardships and
maintain a smooth motion through them um
but that's that can be quite significant
so then other things you pick up is just
psychological skills so you can evaluate
your progress by being well I made a
mistake there but I noticed I made a
mistake
you know I eisah came to that temptation
but I held out a little bit longer than
I did before and just becoming I think
one of the best ways to starting
stoicism is just this mindfulness or
more awareness of kind of psychological
processes and how they function people
talk a lot about journaling in this
respect as a helpful tool to that in
terms of in terms of other systems I
would say what any ethical system should
have you should have a consistency
between when we look at it as moral
education and not just theoretical I
think a good way to evaluate it is
consistency between beliefs and actions
right so for the Stoics there there's
always consistency between beliefs and
actions if you believe something you
will do it so if you have a problem in
your actions you have a problem your
beliefs and you need to re-evaluate and
be honest with yourself but for other
schools of thought like Aristotle or
something like this there there's a
animalistic side there's a habituation
aspect so I think a good way to gauge
progress is to just gauge well if I
think X is good you know if I think it's
good to work out and reach out to my
family and be kind in people I see and
journal twice a day am i doing these
kind of things so is there a connection
between what I set out in my mind is
good plans and the way that I act
because regardless of what your value
system is if that connection is broken
you're you're never going to be able to
manifest that value system so for me
that is that is a really good way of
gauging progress I would rather have
someone who is ignorant but consistent
then someone who seems knowledgeable but
is inconsistent because the
inconsistency it becomes
perhaps more complicated where the issue
is if someone is consistent you just
need to educate them or change their
opinion so I think that's a good way to
evaluate your own progress regardless
what you believe am I consistent do I do
what I think is good do I avoid what I
think is that
mmm-hmm very cool so well-well
understeer Michael before we go to
closing thoughts do you have any kind of
closing words yourself on anything that
was said today yeah that was my first
time like trying to flush that out in
time please I mean please anybody if
you're more interested in it continue to
like reach out to me I would love to
talk about it casually I'm really
interested in this stuff but the picture
that I wanted to give was just that um
there there there's a there's a kind of
an overall project that you're engaging
in and and if you if you want to
transform yourself educate yourself in
that project and take part in that
project not just in certain concepts
like they cut the economy of control can
be helpful but there there's more to
stoicism to flesh out and then another
thing I guess is this is seeing this
difference and highlighting this
difference between you know what you
take to be good and how you act and
looking at a project of moral education
as I guess that pursuit of consistency
that pursuit of acting in accordance
with what you take to be good and I
guess I just want to leave off with it
with how important I think that project
is and recognizing that project as being
separate in some ways from just the
study of ethics with just the study of
philosophy theoretic khumba thanks
everybody I really enjoyed it I really
appreciated appreciative time yeah so
I'll make some announcements in a moment
but Michael thanks so much my friend for
coming to the stoah that was lovely I'd
love to have you back and thanks
everyone for the wonderful questions
today so for the next events at the
stoah you visit the website and you can
also sign up for the mailing list three
of these are going to be rescheduled but
the next one is going to be a more fact
a sort of meditation exercise on April
1st at 7 p.m. I think I said Wednesday
and then when after that is on a
Thursday with our friend Michael Adam
Robert from the side view he's doing a
philosophy the practice for death and
dying that should be an exciting one so
I'm viewing the stoah and this time of
need as a gift of everyone to freely use
and if you're inspired to provide a gift
in return you can go to the store
website and check out the gift economy
section at the bottom of the page for
more information
all right so thanks everyone thank you